Guide to the Hamilton Basso Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Hamilton Basso papers
1861-1975
YCAL MSS 57
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.5
(22 boxes)
Manuscripts, letters, and research material document the life of best-selling novelist Hamilton Basso.
Other Storage Formats: Oversize
Basso, Hamilton, 1904-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Yale Collection of American Literature by Mr. Basso and his widow between 1962 and 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 22: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
HAMILTON BASSO (1904-1964)
Joseph Hamilton Basso was born September 5, 1904 in New Orleans, Louisiana. His early years were spent in the French Quarter of the city, where his grandfather, an Italian immigrant, had established a successful shoe factory. He attended Tulane University, first studying law, but eventually concentrating on journalism and literature, though he did not take a degree. The change in his scholarly interests was precipitated by his association with a group of southern writers who contributed to the Double Dealer, published in New Orleans, the magazine that would eventually publish the first of Basso's own work. Included in this group were writers with whom Basso established lasting friendships, including Sherwood Anderson, William Faulkner, and Edmund Wilson.
In 1926, Basso moved to New York City, establishing himself for a few years in Greenwich Village. He soon moved back to his native New Orleans, where he progressively established himself as a writer and editor at all three of the city's newspapers, including the Times-Picayune. His first novel, the semi-autobiographic Relics and Angels, was published in 1929. The work garnered little acclaim and Basso would later dismiss it as a piece of juvenilia. His next work, Beauregard, the Great Creole (1933), a biography of the Confederate general, was a success, allowing Basso to move to the mountain retreat Pisgah Forest, North Carolina to work on his next novel, accompanied by his wife, Etolia (née Simmons) and their infant son, Keith.
Basso's efforts of the 1930s established him as a novelist of note. His Cinnamon Seed (1934) was well received, as was In Their Own Image (1935) and Courthouse Square (1936), which was optioned to be made into a motion picture. Days Before Lent, published in 1939, became widely acclaimed, winning the Southern Writer's Award for 1940. The film version of the novel, retitled Holiday for Sinners, was released 12 years later. Sun in Capricorn, a novel about the struggle of a Yale graduate against the wiles of a southern politician named Gilgo Slade, who was fashioned after Huey Long, was issued in 1940. In 1943, Basso published Mainstream, a collection of profiles of famous Americans, including Franklin D. Roosevelt.
During the productive years of the 1930s and 1940s, Basso resumed his editorial work by moving to New York to write for several nationally known magazines. Beginning with New Republic in 1935-37, and continuing at Time from 1942-43, Basso eventually established himself as an associate editor at the New Yorker in 1943, a position he held until 1964. The New Yorker gave him the opportunity to work with a variety of other writers and to publish his own short fiction and nonfiction.
The World from Jackson Square, a collection of writings about New Orleans, published in 1948, was done in conjunction with his wife. In 1954, Basso published what is likely his most widely-read book, The View from Pompey's Head. The novel, concerning the conflicting emotions of a Southern expatriate who must confront his heritage when he is called back to his hometown, the fictional Pompey's Head, South Carolina, stayed on the best-seller lists for the better part of a year. The movie, made from the book the following year, proved to be just as successful.
Though Basso and his family settled in Weston, Connecticut in the 1940s, he had a passion for travel. Many of his voyages would provide background for his work. After writing several short pieces for Holiday magazine, Basso issued some of his essays as a collection, titled A Quota of Seaweed, in 1960.
The Light Infantry Ball, a prequel to The View from Pompey's Head and the second in a unfinished trilogy about the town, was issued in 1961. Basso's final novel, A Touch of the Dragon, was published shortly after he died of cancer on May 13, 1964 in New Haven, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The Hamilton Basso Papers consist of letters, manuscripts, photographs, legal and financial documents, and printed material concerning the working and publishing career of the author. The papers span the years 1851-1975, but are concentrated in the period 1929-64.
The collection is housed in 22 boxes and consists of three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers. Box 21 contains Oversize material. Box 22 contains Restricted Fragile Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, covers the years 1927-73. Included here are letters to and from Hamilton Basso and his family, colleagues, readers and publishing companies. The letters from Hamilton Basso to his wife Etolia discuss his activities while away on a series of trips between 1942 and 1960. Letters from February and March 1942 involve Basso's sojourn in Florida where he met Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings. Between 1957 and 1960, Basso traveled to Rio de Janeiro, the South Seas, Scandinavia, and Finland to do research for articles. His letters reflect his admiration for foreign settings and his interactions with natives in both urban and rural areas. Basso later corresponded with many people he met during this period, including the Danielsson family and Emmerik Jensen.
Basso's professional correspondence involved a number of publishing companies and fellow authors. Letters from Thomas Wolfe, written from 1935 until his death in 1938, concern Wolfe's growing notoriety and friends such as F. Scott Fitzgerald. A 28-page letter from Wolfe to Maxwell Perkins dated December 15, 1936 discusses Wolfe's personal philosophy, his writing, and his opinion of influential books such as Ulysses. Maxwell Perkins's letters to Hamilton Basso from August and October 1938 concern Thomas Wolfe before and after the author's death.
Jade Snow-Wong, a sculptor from San Francisco, corresponded with Basso in the mid-1950s and sent him copies of letters written during her trip to Japan, Hong Kong, and India in 1953. During this same period, Basso received a number of fan letters from readers of his best-selling novel, The View from Pompey's Head. Many of these can be found in the "Letter" general folders.
Correspondence with publishing companies reveals the often arduous process of negotiation. The Doubleday & Co., Inc. letters from 1955 reflect the success of The View from Pompey's Head, while later letters from 1962 concern the growing incompatibility between author and publisher.
Series II, Writings, covering the years 1878-1964, contains drafts of most of Hamilton Basso's later works and a number of short pieces written early in his career. The first subseries covers books written by or contributed to by Hamilton Basso. The View from Pompey's Head exists in three versions. A draft typescript is followed by a setting typescript, which was made into a final galley proof for the book. These stages are evident for other titles such as A Quota of Seaweed. The Light Infantry Ball also includes an advance proof of the book and several folders of notes, both written and collected by Basso in preparation for this tale of the Civil War period.
A Touch of the Dragon, Basso's final published work, exists in several stages of development. Begun as a short story entitled "Edwina and the Kangaroo," this story went through at least three distinct drafts before being typeset for publication. The pages of the first and second drafts are not in precise numerical order, because numerous additions and duplicate pages which had to be kept in the sequence in which they were received.
An unpublished novel, The Swing of the Compass, also has many variant pages intermingled in its separate drafts. Draft 3 represents the most cohesive text of this book. Included before the drafts are files of notes, typewritten outlines, character sketches, and printed materials which help trace the development of the Basso's idea from a storyline called "Adam's Profession" to the final 378-page manuscript.
Sun in Capricorn, Basso's 1942 novel about southern politics, is present in several forms, exhibiting a different process of revision than that seen with other manuscripts. For a Popular Library edition of the book in 1961, Basso took copies of his original hardcover novel and revised its pages, making additions and deletion by inserting typewritten notes throughout. One copy of the original hardcover novel contains notes for a play based on the book, while another was used as a setting copy for the paperback edition.
Basso contributed the introduction to Exploration of the Valley of the Amazon by William Lewis Herndon in a reprinted edition of this title from 1952. Drafts of his essay and the final galley proofs are included here as is a setting typescript of another work of fiction, The Green Room, from 1949.
The second subseries, Shorter Works, contains many short stories from Basso's early years in New York and New Orleans. Many of these stories center around a character named Quimby. Profiles of writers (Thomas Wolfe, Eugene O'Neill) and notes for various projects (The USA, Cuba, 1952, Letters from America) make up the later works in this subseries.
Series III, Other Papers, contains financial, legal and printed materials, and photographs. Included here are copies of contracts for publishing and filming rights to several of Basso's books and royalty receipts from the 1950s and 1960s. The printed materials contain a variety of items categorized by the work or subject to which they pertain. Found in the folder for The View from Pompey's Head are newspaper clippings of reviews of the novel, a map of the town of Pompey's Head, and advertising flyers and posters for the British edition of the book, which was entitled simply Pompey's Head.
Writings by Others includes a sketchy profile of Thomas Wolfe by Robert Sadow, as well as a typewritten carbon copy of Wolfe's own work, "The Child by Tiger." Two versions of the radio adaptation of Basso's novel The Green Room, retitled "The Great Lady" by Fletcher Markle and Robert Wallstein, are found here, as well.
Box 21 contains Oversize material from the Writings series. The Restricted Fragile Papers in Box 22 consist of the originals for which preservation copies have been made.
Double-dealer; Holiday; New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); American literature -- 20th Century; American literature -- Southern States; Fiction -- 20th Century; Historical fiction; Voyages and travels; Authors; Novelists; Basso, Etolia; Basso, Hamilton, 1904-1964; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898-1989; Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1873-1945; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984; Herndon, William Lewis, 1813-1857 ( Exploration of the valley of the Amazon); Lindsay, Howard, 1889-1968; Perkins, Maxwell E. (Maxwell Evarts), 1884-1947; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972; Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938; Wong, Jade Snow
- Correspondence, 1927-73; Series I; 1.5' (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Anderson, Sherwood, 1929-30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "A" general, 1950-62 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barker, Lee
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Doubleday & Co., Inc., Box 2 folder 41-44
  - Barrau, J., 1959-60 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Basso, Etolia, 1942-64 (Box 1, Folder 4-15)
  - Basso, Keith, 1942-50 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Benjamin, Ben, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Boyle, Kay, 1958 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1943-61 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brown, Ned, 1949-56 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "B" general, 1933-64 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Cahn, Edmond H., 1954-61 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Caldwell, Erskine, 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Catton, Bruce, 1955-56 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Challman, Jean C., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1941, 1946, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chase, Marion, 1950-53, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Chase, Stuart, 1956, 1961
  - Civil War Round Table of New York, 1954, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Collins, W. A. R.
    See: Wm Collins Sons & Co., Ltd., Box 4 folder 119
  - Columbia Broadcasting System, 1949, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cousins, Margaret, 1955-62 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cousins, Norman, 1963 Sep 9
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1938-64 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Crowell-Collier Publishing Co., 1961-62 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - cummings, e. e., 1954 Apr 12 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd., 1942-43 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "C" general, 1949-62, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Danielsson, Bengt, 1959-60, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Danielsson, Marie-Therèse, 1959-62, n.d.
  - Danielsson, Marnia, 1959
  - DeVoto, Bernard, 1943, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - DeVoy, S. Elizabeth
    See: Charles Scribner's Sons, Box 1 folder 27
  - DeVries, Peter, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Doubleday & Co., Inc., 1952-68 (Box 2, Folder 41-44)
  - "D" general, 1943-62 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Ellsworth, Ellen, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Encyclopædia Britannica, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "E" general, 1953-60 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Faulkner, William, 1948 Sep 15 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Ferguson, Otis, 1935-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Fitzgerald, F. Scott, 1936, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "F" general, 1949-61 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Gelb, Arthur, 1961 Dec 5 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Glasgow, Ellen, 1936-44 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    See also: H. Blair Rouse, Box 3 folder 96
  - "G" general, 1949-62 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Harlan, John M., 1959-64 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Harper & Brothers, 1949-60 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Hellman, Lillian, 1949-59, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Hersey, John, 1964 Jan 27
  - Holiday Magazine, 1949-60 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Hughes, Emile, 1938-45, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - H. W. Wilson Company, 1952-53 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "H" general, 1949-63 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Institute for International Education, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Issler, Anne, 1959-60
  - "I" general, 1951-54 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Jensen, Emmerik, 1960-62 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Jensen, Jens, 1960 Oct 5
  - "J" general, 1936-58 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Keyes, Frances Parkinson, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Knittel, Robert
  - Kronenberger, Louis, 1955, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - "K" general, 1952-58 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Laffont, Robert, 1959-61 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Lamb, Mary Wright, 1960
  - Lindsay, Howard, 1955-62 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - "L" general, 1933-62 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - McFee, William, 1950-60 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1949-59 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Marshall, Donald S., 1959-62 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Maugham, W. Somerset, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Methuen & Co., 1937-38 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, 1963 Nov 9
  - Monsarrat, Nicholas, 1956 Feb 28 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Museum Press, 1951
  - "M" general, 1933-60 (Box 3, Folder 80-81)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1955-56 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    See also: Louis Kronenberg, Box 2 folder 69
  - New American Library, 1952-53
  - New Yorker, 1952-63 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - New York Herald Tribune, 1954-55
  - New York Times, 1960 Oct 2 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Nowell, Elizabeth, 1949-51
  - "N" general, 1950-55 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - O'Brien, Edmond, 1959, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Ogburn, Charlton, 1950 Apr 6
  - O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey, 1948-57 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Ong, Connie
    See: Jade Snow Wong, Box 4 folder 125-27
  - "O" general, 1933-63 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Perkins, Maxwell, 1933-41 (Box 3, Folder 89-91)
  - Players Club, 1952, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    See also: Howard Lindsay, Box 2 folder 72
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1935 July 20
  - Pyles, Horacio, 1953-54 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - "P" general, 1953-62 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Rawlings, Marjorie Kinnan, 1944 Jun 18 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Reader's Digest Books, 1960, 1962
  - Rouse, H. Blair, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Russell & Volkening, Inc., 1963-73 (Box 3, Folder 97-99)
  - Russell, Diarmuid
    See: Russell & Volkening, Inc., Box 3 folder 97-99
  - "R" general, 1949-61 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Senhausen, C. B., 1959 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Shaeffer, Louis, 1958
  - Snow-Wong, Jade
  - Stimson, J. Frank, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - "S" general, 1933-62 (Box 3, Folder 103-04)
  - Taylor, Garland F., 1953, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Thurber, James, 1952
  - Turnbull, Andrew W., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Turner, Joan, 1960, 1962
  - Twentieth Century Fox, 1949, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - "T" general, 1949-63 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Udall, Stewart L., 1955-56 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Undset, Sigrid, 1947 Oct 8
  - "U" general, 1954-61 (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Van Doren, Irita
    See: New York Herald Tribune, Box 3 folder 83
  - Van E. Kohn, John S., 1962 Mar 21 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Viking Press, 1962-64 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Volkening, Henry
  - "V" general, 1952, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Waring, T. R., 1954-56 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Weber, William C.
  - Wegner, Christian, 1955-59 (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - West, Francis, 1959-62 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Wheaton, Mabel Wolfe, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Wheelock, Jack, 1935-56 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Wm Collins Sons & Co., Ltd., 1954-63 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1927-62 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Wolfe, Thomas, 1935-38, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 121-24)
  - Wong, Jade Snow, 1952-56 (Box 4, Folder 125-27)
  - "W" general, 1938-62 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Yale University, 1950, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    See also: John S. Van E. Kohn, Box 4 folder 111
  - Yellin, David, 1958
  - Zehring, Jeannette, 1950 Apr 10 (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Unidentified, 1932-62 (Box 4, Folder 131)
- Writings, 1878-1964; Series II; 6.25' (15 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is divided into two subseries. The first, Books, is arranged alphabetically by title. Under title, folders are arranged according to the development of the manuscript, with separate drafts and stages noted. Many drafts contain variant pages, duplicate pages and additions. These have been preserved in the order in which they were received. The second subseries, Shorter Works, is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - BOOKS
    - Adam's Profession
      See: The Swing of the Compass, Box 11 folder 207
    - Chain of Command
      - Notes: holograph, typescript and printed material, 1878-1957, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Edwina and Lord Kangaroo
      See: A Touch of the Dragon, Box 14 folder 256
    - Edwina and the Kangaroo
    - Exploration of the Valley of the Amazon by William Lewis Herndon
      - Notes, 1951, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 133)
      - Galley proof, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 134-36)
        See also: Oversize, Box 21, folder 410
    - The Green Room
      - Setting typescript, corrected, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 137-42)
    - The Light Infantry Ball
      - Notes
        - Background information (Box 5, Folder 143)
          See also: Oversize, Box 21, folder 411
        - Character, scene, and character outlines (Box 5, Folder 144)
        - Cuts, incidents, and episodes (Box 5, Folder 145)
        - Discarded manuscript pages, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 146)
        - Individual outlines (Box 5, Folder 147)
        - "War stuff", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
      - Draft typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 149-61)
      - Setting typescript, corrected, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 162-66)
      - Setting typescript, corrected, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 167-74)
      - Setting typescript, carbon, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 175-84)
      - Setting typescript, carbon, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 185-89)
      - Final galley proof 1, corrected, 1959 Jan-Feb (Box 8, Folder 190)
      - Final galley proof 2, corrected, 1959 Mar (Box 8, Folder 191)
      - Advance proof, uncorrected, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 192)
    - A Quota of Seaweed
      - Notes, 1958, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 193)
      - Setting typescript, corrected, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 194-99)
    - Sun in Capricorn
      - Explanatory notes, 1962 Jul 17 (Box 9, Folder 200)
      - 1st edition book, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 201)
      - 1st edition book: author's copy with notes for play based on book, 1942, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 202)
      - 1st edition book: with author's rough notes, changes and additions, 1942, [1959?] (Box 10, Folder 203)
      - 1st edition book: disbound pages, corrected with additions, used as setting copy, 1942, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 204)
      - 1st edition book: extra printer's copy with author's changes and additions, with bookjacket, 1942-61 (Box 11, Folder 205)
      - Paperback edition book, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 206)
    - The Swing of the Compass
      - Background material, 1954-61, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 207-08)
        See also: Photographs - Motuvini, Box 20, folder 393
      - Notebooks, 1961, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 209-10)
      - Notecards, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 211)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 212)
      - Revised manuscript pages: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 213)
      - Revised manuscript pages: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 214-16)
      - Draft 1: typescript, corrected, [1961] (Box 12, Folder 217-31)
      - Draft 2: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 232-37)
      - Draft 2: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 238-46)
      - Draft 3: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 247-55)
    - A Touch of the Dragon
      - Short story: "Edwina and the Kangaroo": typescript, annotated (Box 14, Folder 256)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 257)
      - Draft 1: typescript, corrected and annotated (Box 14, Folder 258-68)
      - Draft 2: typescript, corrected and annotated (Box 15, Folder 269-79)
      - Draft 3: typescript, corrected, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 280-82)
      - Draft 3: typescript, corrected, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 283-85)
      - Setting typescript, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 286-88)
      - Setting typescript: carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 289-93)
    - The View from Pompey's Head
      - Notes, 1951-54, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 294)
      - Draft: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 295-97)
      - Draft: typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 298-12)
      - Setting typescript, corrected, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 313-16)
      - Setting typescript, corrected, 1954 (Box 18, Folder 317-28)
      - Galley proof, corrected, 1954 (Box 18, Folder 329)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - Article and essay possibilities: notes, 1962, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 330)
    - Article on Boswell Papers: magazine clipping, [1949?] (Box 19, Folder 331)
    - Article on Brazil: notes, 1947, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 332-33)
    - "Attitude": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 334)
    - "A Burden of Sin": typescript, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 335)
    - "A Burial": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 336)
    - "Conversation with Eugene O'Neill": typescript, annotated, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 337)
    - "Cuba, 1952": notebook, 1952 Mar (Box 19, Folder 338)
    - "Dead Leaves [The Pole]": typescript, annotated, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 339)
    - "A Debutante"" typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 340)
    - "Edwina and the Primitives"
      See: A Touch of the Dragon, Boxes 14-16, folders 256-292
    - "An Epilogue": typescript, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 341)
    - "Exam": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 342)
    - "Finale": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 343)
    - "Finesse": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 344)